<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The accuser sham'd: or, A pair of bellows to blow off that dust cast upon John Fry, a Member of Parliament, by Col: John Downs, likewise a Member of Parliament, who by the confederacy and instigation of some, charged the said John Fry of blasphemy &amp; error to the Honorable House of Commons. Whereunto is annexed, a word to the priests, lawyers, Royalists, self-seekers, and rigid-Presbyterians. Also a brief ventilation of that chaffie and absurd opinion, of three persons or subsistences in the Godhead. / By the accused John Fry.</title>
            <author>Fry, John, 1609-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84945</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2254</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E544_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E624_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32440</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872322</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872322</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165806</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84945)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165806)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 84:E544[7], 96:E624[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The accuser sham'd: or, A pair of bellows to blow off that dust cast upon John Fry, a Member of Parliament, by Col: John Downs, likewise a Member of Parliament, who by the confederacy and instigation of some, charged the said John Fry of blasphemy &amp; error to the Honorable House of Commons. Whereunto is annexed, a word to the priests, lawyers, Royalists, self-seekers, and rigid-Presbyterians. Also a brief ventilation of that chaffie and absurd opinion, of three persons or subsistences in the Godhead. / By the accused John Fry.</title>
                  <author>Fry, John, 1609-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Harris, and are to be sold at his house on Addle hill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Febr. 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The date in the imprint appears to be incorrect. The Thomason catalog dates this item in February 1651 and a reply "Divine Beames of Glorious Light .. 1651" is dated March 1, 1651.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy E.624[2]: [illegible].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Downes, John, fl. 1666 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament. --  House of Commons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prohibited books --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165806:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> The ACCUSER ſham'd: OR, A pair of Bellows To Blow off that Duſt caſt upon <hi>JOHN FRY,</hi> A Member of PARLIAMENT, by Col: <hi>John Downs,</hi> likewiſe a Member of Parliament, Who by the Confederacy and Inſtigation of ſome, charged the ſaid JOHN FRY of Blaſphemy &amp; Error To the Honorable Houſe of COMMONS.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is annexed,</p>
            <p>A word to the Prieſts, Lawyers, Royaliſts, Self-Seekers, and Rigid-Presbyterians.</p>
            <p>Alſo a brief Ventilation of that chaffie and abſurd Opinion, of <hi>Three Perſons or Subſiſtences in the Godhead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the accuſed JOHN FRY.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Rom 10 2.</bibl> I bear them record, they have a zeal, but not according to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Acts 17. 23, 24, &amp;c.</bibl> For as I paſſed by, and beheld your devotions, I found an Altar with this inſcription, <hi>To the unknown God:</hi> whom there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye ignorantly worſhip, him declare I unto you. God that made the world, and all things therein, ſeeing that he is Lord of heaven and earth, dwelleth not in Temples made with hands.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Harris,</hi> and are to be ſold at his houſe on Addle hill. Febr. 1648.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:165806:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:165806:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Do wave any Epiſtle, either Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, or to the Reader, for theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons:</p>
            <p>Firſt, To avoid ſuſpition of guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the crimes laid againſt me, as if I needed a protector.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To ſhun the thoughts of Cenſoriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as though I thought that Truth could not walk abroad without a Paſs-Port.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, To decline that unworthineſs (which I think ſome men are guilty of) of begging mens ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages to what I aſſert.</p>
            <p>I did not adventure thus to ſtraggle abroad, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out much oppoſition in my ſelf, which chiefly was the conſciouſneſs of mine inſufficiency to abide the Teſt of judicious mens Cenſures, for method, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity, and aptneſs of words and ſence.</p>
            <p>But rather then I would lye under ſuch a charge of Error and Blaſphemy, I choſe to lay open my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the world, in point of art, being ſtirred up too by ſome of my (I am perſwaded) very cordial friends.</p>
            <p>What ſatisfaction I ſhall give to the world, I am not much troubled at, becauſe I ſeek not the ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of al; if by this I may avoid the cenſure of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is the height of my deſire; however, this I am ſure of, mine own conſcience doth not condemn me.</p>
            <p>I were a ſingular man, if I had not adverſaries, ſuch a man is certainly very miſerable, according to that in <hi>Luke</hi> 6. 26. <hi>We be to you when all men ſhall ſpeak well</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:165806:3"/> 
               <hi>of you, for ſo did their fathers to the falſe prophets:</hi> And therefore the having of adverſaries is rather a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort then a trouble.</p>
            <p>Upon the beſt inquiry into, and recollection of paſſages for ſome years laſt paſt, I cannot finde that I have gained any Enemies, but either for adhering to the publike intereſt, oppoſing of ſelf-intereſts ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my truſt, or declaring my opinion in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion; for the latter, I think advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages have been taken of me, more in policy then piety, ſome being glad of ſuch an opportunity (as I have often been credibly informed) to remove me out of the way to their private ends.</p>
            <p>I am not diſcouraged a whit, to think that in a time when the Preſs is ſo free, and accute wits ſo much in view, that mine muſt come in the rear of all; if that were the conſideration, I ſhould not have manifeſted ſo much folly as to be in Print; that is proper for his thoughts that writes more to ſhew his parts, then for one that is neceſſitated to vindicate himſelf from ſo foul an aſperſion as is caſt upon me: if any man ſhall ſay, I am too tender of my reputation, I wiſh him to make it his own caſe, and if that will not change his Opinion, he muſt give me leave to doubt whether he be in good earneſt or no.</p>
            <p>I am not very greedy to ſolicite ſtrangers to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come my friends in this particular, my deſires are to confirm my old acquaintance and Chriſtian friends; yet I would not be wanting ſo far as 'tis meet, to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie thoſe that have nothing to lead their judgements but reports. I ſhall therefore give my poſitive denyal to my Charge, together with my opinion in the point, to be put in one ſcale, and but his bold and untrue aſſertion in the other, and if this will not at leaſt ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165806:3"/> their judgement of me, I appeal to all the world, whether they are upon grounds of equity or no.</p>
            <p>I hear that many who have onely heard of me, and had good thoughts of me, are now ſtaggering up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the report that I deny the God-head of the Son; if by what I have, and ſhall ſay, I cannot regain their good opinions, their uncharitableneſs will more wound themſelves then me, for were it ſo that no man will believe me, mine own conſcience, as to my ſelf, is inſtead of a thouſand witneſſes to acquit me before the Judge of all.</p>
            <p>I hear that ſome ſay (upon what grounds I know not) that what I tendred to the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons for their ſatisfaction, is ſo covertly expreſſed, that they conclude I have but deceived them, &amp; that I am ſtill, &amp; have been for a twelve moneth paſt of the opinion, that the ſecond in the Trinity, to wit, Jeſus Chriſt is not God; but how groundleſly they conclude this of me, if I have not loſt all reputation amongſt them, will be very evident by what I hold forth.</p>
            <p>That I have many Enemies, I doubt not, and ſuch as are not of petty profeſſions and repute, as namely, Prieſts, Lawyers, Cavies, Self-ſeekers, and Rigid-Presbyterians, of all theſe not a few: to ſuch mens ways I profeſs my ſelf an Enemy, but not to their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; and till I ſee ſome amendment of them in their trades, I ſhall not, I hope, alter my thoughts of them; how the Goſpel, Law, mens Eſtates, and the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Freedoms of the people are bought and ſold, I am not altogether a ſtranger to; and what palpable contradictions there are in theſe mens profeſſions and actions, I ſhall endeavor to clear.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Firſt, let us take a brief ſurvey of the Prieſt, but if
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:165806:4"/> any ſhall ſay there is too much gall in my pen for uſing this word <hi>Prieſt,</hi> I ſhall refer him to what the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 11. <hi>Where there is a change of the Prieſthood, there is of neceſsity a change of the Law;</hi> then it will follow, where the Law is not aboliſhed, there the Prieſthood is not aboliſhed; and that the Law is kept on foot, I ſhall inſtance in one particular onely (though I could ſhew their legality in many things) as that of Tythes: Was not the Tythes due under the Law to the Prieſts, as ſuch onely? and do our Tythe and Parſonage-mongers, claim it upon any other ſcore? They like the profit, but not the title the Law giveth them; they would alter the term Prieſt, into the name of a Miniſter of the Goſpel: but how well this becometh them, their preaching and practice conſidered, I profeſs, I think a man of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary capacity can ſee without a pair of ſpectacles. Our Savior Chriſt in that Commiſſion to the Preachers of the Goſpel, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 7. commands them, <hi>Go preach, ſaying, The Kingdom of Heaven is at hand.</hi> Verſe 8. <hi>Freely ye have received, freely give.</hi> Verſe 14. <hi>Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall not receive you, nor hear your words, when you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of that houſe or City, ſhake off the duſt of your feet.</hi> Luke 9. 5. ſaith, <hi>Shake off the duſt of your feet for a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt them:</hi> This was practiced by <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas, Acts.</hi> 13. 51. <hi>They ſhook off the duſt of their feet againſt them, and came to Iconium:</hi> But is this the practice of theſe Goſpel-Preachers (would be called?) nay, will they not rather ſhake off the duſt of their feet, and be gone from the Saints, where the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is not great, and go among men that ſcorn both them and the Goſpel, for a good fat Parſonage, and there caſt the Goſpel in the beſt maner they can,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:165806:4"/> which is the pearl mentioned, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 7. unto a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Swine, contrary to the command? How eager are many of them for a Gooſe, or a Tythe egg at Eaſter with their Neighbors? if they conceive they have not that which they call their Due, it ſhall make a breach between them, that they will never love one another again: if theſe be Goſpel-Preachers, or if theſe do not ſell the Goſpel, I confeſs I know nothing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Enter Lawyer.</head>
               <p>Who would think that a Gentleman of ſo demure a garb, had ſo much (I had almoſt ſaid knavery) craft under his Sattin-Cap and long Robe? put him what Caſe you will, he wil tell you 'tis good, and perchance he ſpeaks truth; but the ſilly Clyent knoweth not the meaning, he thinks that his Cauſe is good, but there is another meaning in it, which is this, it is good for the Lawyers, for they ſhall get money by it: Doth not too much experience manifeſt this? There is a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe called <hi>Caninus-appetitus,</hi> let us ſee whether they are not ſick of this, eſpecially thoſe that are any thing eminent, and have the priviledge to plead within the Bar: Do not many finde their appetites are ſo great, that whereas heretofore ten or twenty ſhillings would ſerve their turn, now you muſt give them five or ten pounds, and yet their panches hardly ſatisfied? Nay, do not many of them take a mans money and not do his work? Doth it not many times fall out, that while the Lawyer is pleading in one Court for one Clyent, another of his Clyents Cauſe is hearing in another? And when it is the Lawyers fault to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſo many Cauſes, that he cannot give attendance to them all, Do they reſtore the Fees they have taken,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165806:5"/> though the man be undone for depending upon him? if there be any ſuch, for my part, I neither know them, nor have I heard of them, but it may be there are black Swans.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A word to the Cavies.</head>
               <p>How theſe have endeavored to ſell their own and their Neighbors Freedoms for a meſs of pottage, I mean the Kings favor, is ſo apparent and obvious in every eye, that I need not uſe arguments to prove it; and therefore I ſhall onely ſay this to them, Sithence what they have reaped of all their labor, is but ſcorn and contempt of all honeſt true-hearted Engliſh men, and a Sequeſtration to boot, I hope they will take warning for the future, by what is paſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the next place comes the Self-ſeeker.</head>
               <p>This Gentleman, notwithſtanding his falſe vizard of zeal to the publike intereſt (which mask is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe put on by all that I have to do with now) is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily diſcovered: Do they think that thoſe which have raiſed handſome Eſtates out of nothing, and vaſt Eſtates out of mean Eſtates, ſince our general calamity upon the ruine of many, as well friend as foe, can deſerve any other title then Self-ſeekers? and though they bleſs themſelves in their miſ-gotten goods, that any honeſt hearts can but condemn them for their unſeaſonable building their neſts ſo high? let them read what the Prophet <hi>Haggai</hi> ſaith, <hi>ch.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>Is it time for ye, O ye, to dwell in your ceiled houſes, and this houſe lie waſte?</hi> So may I ſay, Is it a time for you, O ye Self-ſeekers, to ceil and raiſe up your houſes, when
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:165806:5"/> the Nation lies waſte? Is not this a prepoſterous way, to raiſe your Eſtates upon your Brethrens ruine? I ſpeak to thoſe chiefly, that contrary to the Self-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ordinance, ſtill keep the Offices of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, the profit of which, eſpecially in ſuch a time as this is, ought (allowing a competent Sallery to thoſe that execute them) to be converted to the publike uſe: And though I ſpeak principally to ſuch, yet I condemn all thoſe new made Officers too, that have enriched themſelves (whiles others, better af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to the Nation, have been undone) by the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize, Sequeſtrations, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the next place a word to Rigid Sir <hi>John Presbyter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>How zealous this Gentleman is in his way, would be needleſs to hold forth, becauſe he is ſo wel known; but the blindeneſs of his zeal is not as generally known, and therefore I ſhall ſay ſomething to that. I ſhall propound two Queſtions:</p>
               <p>Firſt, Whether a man may be queſtioned in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Divine onely?</p>
               <p>Secondly, If ſo, How, and upon what grounds he challengeth this Juriſdiction, more then a man of a different judgement?</p>
               <p>To the firſt I anſwer, I am altogether unſatisfied, that the Magiſtrate can take Cognizance upon Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Rules which we ought to walk by, or call any man to an account for any thing, but what is really prejudicial to his Neighbor, in his perſon, eſtate or good Name; becauſe it is ſaid, <hi>Who art thou that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneſt another? he either ſtandeth or falleth to his own maſter.</hi> And I challenge any one to ſhew me a Text
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:165806:6"/> in all the New Teſtament, for ſuch a practice; if they cannot, and yet will practice it, do they not condemn the New Teſtament of imperfection in matters of Rules, or elſe uſurp this authority becauſe they will, and have no other Reaſon but their will for it?</p>
               <p>But to the ſecond: Suppoſe ſuch a thing, yet I am not convinced by any thing I ever heard or read, that he hath right to aſſume this power: If Fire and Fag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got be an Argument, or the deſtroving of men in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, what do they leſs then juſtifie all the perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that ever were made upon the Saints? If this Gentleman could but demonſtrate to me his infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, I ſhould be much ſtaggered; nay, they are ſo far from this, that they dare not ſay ſo much: and if ſo, what is it but the begging of the Queſtion? I wiſh they would remember that ſaying of God, <hi>He that toucheth you, toucheth the apple of mine eye;</hi> and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whether that Propheſie in the Goſpel may not concern them, <hi>The days ſhall come, when they ſhall put you to death, and think they do God good ſervice.</hi> And for that Argument, They that have the power may do it, and the majority of Voyces ought to carry all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: I ſhall anſwer it with that place of the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 13, 14. <hi>Wide is the gate, and broad is the way that leadeth to deſtruction, and many there be that go there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: But ſtrait is the gate, and narrow the way that leadeth to life, and few there be that finde it.</hi> I could ſay much more, but I ſtudy brevity. There is a ſaying amongſt Phyſitians, That when diſeaſes are diſcovered, they are half cured; and that I may not do my work to halves, I ſhall beſtow the beſt skill I can.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>For the Prieſt, I would leave him to the people, ſo as the Diſciples and Apoſtles of Chriſt were; and if
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165806:6"/> they are his Meſſengers, he will ſurely pay them their wages though men wil not: certainly, as they have free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly received, ſo they ought freely to give; and if once I ſaw them of that diſpoſition, I doubt not but God would ſtir up the hearts of men to be as free towards them in their Carnal things, as they are towards the people in Spiritual things: For a Goſpel-people, will be a free-people.</p>
               <p>For the Lawyers cure, I would have the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſtint him in his Fee, and if he exceeded, or took more Cauſes then he could manage, ſo that any man were undone by it, I would have him ſuſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from practiſing, and his Gown pulled over his ears.</p>
               <p>And for the Cavies, I would take them ſhort enough for ever being able to abuſe themſelves and country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men by any power they ſhould be truſted with: I would never put a Sword into his hands, that had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly uſed it to the enſlaving of himſelf and country; and if he will be troubleſom, and not take ſuch fair warning as he hath had, I would ſend him to a New Plantation; for it is pity, and dangerous to have any more of the Breed of him here.</p>
               <p>As for the Self-ſeeker, I would be ſure to truſt him ſo far as I could ſee him, and no farther: And to ſtop this Leaprous diſeaſe, I would not onely give him a Vomit, that he might diſgorge thoſe filthy Morſels he hath ſo greedily ſwallowed, to the prejudice of the Body Politique; but alſo have a ſpecial care, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act eye upon all the Money-vangers for the future, and not let paſs more then a moneth, for the calling of thoſe to an account, who weekly, nay almoſt daily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive money in ſome places, as your Treaſurers in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165806:7"/> Counties, who receive money for the Army, and money for Sequeſtred goods, and Rents, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this proportion of time, according as moneys comes in to all the ſeveral money-takers for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, I would deal with them.</p>
               <p>Rigid Sir <hi>John Presbyter</hi> is as deſperately ſick as any of the reſt, and therefore it will require more art then mine, I fear; but yet I will do my beſt, and what is wanting, let it be ſupplyed by an abler Artiſt. By my caſting of his ſtate, his diſeaſe ſeems to be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of kin to Mr. <hi>Cavies;</hi> and therefore I ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe much of what I did to him. I would almoſt as ſoon put a Sword into the hands of a mad-man, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of a high-flying Presbyter; certainly, the forcing of a mans conſcience by civil Power, is a note beyond the Apoſtles <hi>Ela:</hi> But what do I ſpeak of the Apoſtles and Diſciples of Chriſt? they were puiſns, and lived in the nonage of time; they never ſaw ſuch an Aſſembly of Divines, and a gallant Book called <hi>The Annotations upon the Bible,</hi> which coſt them many years travel. Truly, this Book coſt me Twenty five ſhillings, and if any one will give me but twenty for it again, I will give him thanks, though it be not two pence the worſe for my uſing of it; he that can, or will afford time to read it over, hath more leiſure and liking to it then I. Happily the Pen-men of the New Teſtament writ at a venture, as King <hi>James</hi> did his Book, entituled, <hi>Demonalogy;</hi> and as old Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> of <hi>New-Inn Hall</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> a reputed Conjurer, underſtood King <hi>James</hi> his Book better then himſelf; ſo theſe Gentlemen may the New Teſtament, then the writers of it: If theſe Gentlemen will needs be doing, I would make them Maſters over all the Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lams
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165806:7"/> in <hi>England,</hi> and if that be not work enough, let them go into <hi>America,</hi> and try their newfound expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment there; in my opinion, it is not fit for <hi>Europe,</hi> except as afore. We read <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 6. <hi>That without faith it is impoſsible to pleaſe God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And that faith comes by hearing, and hearing by the word of God,</hi> Rom. 10. 17. <hi>And that faith is a gift,</hi> Epheſians 2. 8. 'Tis true, that at <hi>Rome</hi> where this new firſt diſcovery was made, the Civil Sword hath been uſed to drive men to Heaven whither they would or no, but whether it ever wrought that effect, or was at firſt intended for that end, I very much doubt, whatſoever was pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: And ſince this Opinion was forged there, I wiſh the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> would ſend it from whence it came, and quite baniſh it our Land; Theſe diſeaſes are grown Epidemical, otherwiſe I ſhould have ſpared this labor.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <head>A true Narrative, according to the best ſcrutiny I can make into my thoughts, of what paſt between Col: <hi>Downs</hi> and my ſelf, upon which he accuſed me.</head>
            <p>IN <hi>January</hi> laſt paſt, about the fifteenth day, I was with many other Gentlemen of the Houſe of Commons in the afternoon, in the Committee-Chamber above the Parliament-Houſe, by a fire there; one <hi>Cornelius Holland,</hi> Eſq; a worthy Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment man, and true Patriot to his Countrey (who <hi>Moſes-like,</hi> choſe rather to ſuffer with the people of God, then to be one in the Kings Court, and enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon, as manifeſtly appears by his taking part with the Parliament, and good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this Iſland againſt the King and his God-dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165806:8"/> blades) came to me, and deſired me to go to the Committee of plundered Miniſters, to help free a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter that had lyen in Priſon two or three years for denying the perſonality of Chriſt, to which I gave my ready concurrence, being one of that Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee: Col: <hi>Downs</hi> ſtanding by, and hearing our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, brake out into paſſionate Language, ſaying, He deſerved to lye by it, and to have far greater pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; I would be loath to abuſe the Gentleman as he hath done me, but I take it, he ſaid, he deſerved to be hanged; to which I reply'd, I do not ſee any ground for ſuch a hard cenſure; for I did think, that according to the common acceptation of that word, it could hardly be defended by Scripture; and for my part, I was altogether diſ-ſatisfied with thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of three diſtinct Perſons, or Subſiſtences in the God-head: to which he reply'd, I do not care for the word perſonality, but ſaid, Jeſus Chriſt was God, which I did not apprehend to be the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before us, and this was all that paſt at that time.</p>
            <p>About two or three days after, I met the ſaid Col: <hi>Downs</hi> in the Painted-chamber at Weſtminſter, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we came as Members of the High Court of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, for the Tryal of the King, but being ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what earlier then others, I ſpake to him thus, If it pleaſe you, ſince we have opportunity, for I ſuppoſe the Court will not ſit yet, let us calmly make a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther progreſs into that diſcourſe we entred upon the other day in the Committee-room, and had not time then to proſecute; to which he conſented: but where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I deſired him to diſpute without heat, he could not forbear that. The two main things we inſiſted upon, were theſe:</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:165806:8"/>
            <p> Firſt, the Trinity of perſons in the Unity of the Godhead.</p>
            <p>Secondly, what the Union was between Chriſt and his Saints.</p>
            <p>But as I did not deliver my Opinion poſitively in either, but onely Argumentatively, ſo neither was there any method in our diſcourſe, which hardly can ever be obtained from a paſſionate man: After I had gained his conſent to ſpeak together, as aforeſaid, I began thus, Truly, I do not believe Jeſus Chriſt to be God, after that maner which ſome do hold him forth, for according to my beſt underſtanding of their words and expreſſions, they hold forth three Gods, and I would fain know how it can be demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, that there can be three diſtinct perſons, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtences in one entire being; and for the word <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſistence,</hi> it holds forth no more, in my judgement, of Chriſt his being in the Godhead, then may be affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of every Creature, according to that in <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 24. <hi>In him we live, move, and have our being.</hi> I offered to his conſideration, touching the Saints Union with Chriſt, thoſe Scriptures where it is ſaid, <hi>That Chriſt is the head, and the Saints are the members,</hi> which is in many places of the New Teſtament, and then ſaid, <hi>That whatſoever the head did partake of, that did the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers alſo,</hi> and my foot was as really of my body as my head, but not indeed in ſo excellent a maner: I quoted that Scripture alſo of 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 4. <hi>Whereby are given to us exceeding great and precious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, that by theſe you might be partaker of the Divine Nature:</hi> And walking in a round in our diſcourſe; for as I have ſaid, it was very immethodical, I ſpake of that word <hi>Subſiſtence</hi> again, ſaying, That accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:165806:9"/> to my underſtanding of that word, I might be ſaid to be God too, as well as Jeſus Chriſt, and the like might be affirmed of all other Creatures what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; to which he ſaid, You had beſt ſay the Devil is ſo too: After he had ſpoken this, there was not a word more paſt between us at that time, for the Lord Preſident came into the Chair, which ended our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. I ſuppoſe many more words paſt between us, but this is the ſubſtance of what I ſpake. Had I ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined I ſhould have been called to an accompt for it, 'tis very probable I ſhould have thought upon it more then I did, and ſo have been fitter to give a more large and punctual relation, but I have not dealt unfaithful in any material thing. I have often diſcourſed with many, but I was never ſo injuriouſly and diſcourte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly dealt with in all my life, that I remember; which whether it was not far beneath the part of a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, I leave to the world to judge.</p>
            <p>About nine or ten days after, I was going in the morning from my Lodging at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> up into the City, about ſome occaſions I had there, and by the way I met with a Noble Lord, my very good and much honored friend, and after I had humbly ſaluted him, he ſaid he would tell me ſome news, I liſtned to him, being very willing to hear what it was, he told me that Col: <hi>Downs</hi> had adviſed with Mr. Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to frame a charge againſt me of Blaſphemy, which was, That I ſhould ſay, That Jeſus Chriſt was not God: I muſt confeſs, I was ſomewhat affected with it upon the ſudden, but I thanked his Lordſhip, and told him, I doubted not but to anſwer it well enough, and took my leave of him, haſting about my buſineſs, that I might return, if poſſible, before the Houſe ſate,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:165806:9"/> that in caſe they were reſolved to charge me, I might be preſent at the report to make my defence; but yet I muſt profeſs, when I had conſidered it, I did not think Col: <hi>Downs</hi> could be inſtigated, upon a private broken diſcourſe as that was, to charge me in the higheſt Court of <hi>England:</hi> For, knowing with what minde I diſcourſed, and the confuſedneſs of it too, it ſeemed to be ſo far beyond the Rules of Civility, Chriſtianity and Prudence, that I thought it incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that a Gentleman ſhould ſo much forget himſelf. But the Gentlemans zeal, or rather weakneſs (for I profeſs I think he was abuſed by thoſe that ſet him on, they feeling his pulſe, made a Mountain of a Mole-hill, and ſo heightned his ſpirit, that, poor Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, he thought himſelf bound in Conſcience to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute me as he did) tranſported him beyond all rules. I may be bold to ſay, without partiality, becauſe I have heard divers Gentlemen of that judgement, That he much tranſgreſſed the bounds of Civility; and certainly, it was not done like a Chriſtian, for they will admoniſh one another, and uſe all fair means of converſion, and upon good grounds; ſo that they are incorrigible, before they will lay open their faults to thoſe in Authority. And if it were prudentially done to engage his Reputation in a buſineſs of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, upon his ſingle Teſtimony, I am much miſtaken. I think a wiſe man, if he had thought me of that opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by what diſcourſe he heard from me, &amp; conceived himſelf obliged in Conſcience to diſcover it, would have asked me before witneſs, whether I did hold that Opinion, or no? that upon my owning of it before others, he might with clearneſs have charged me, without the leaſt appearance of reflection upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:165806:10"/> I ſhall recommend that place of Scripture to him, and all of his minde, for their direction for the future, it is <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 1. <hi>Brethren, if any man be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken in a fault, ye which are ſpiritual, reſtore ſuch a one in the ſpirit of meekneſs, conſidering thy ſelf, leſt thou al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be tempted.</hi> I made ſo quick a return out of <hi>London,</hi> that I came to the Houſe before the Speaker was in the Chair; I looked over all the Houſe for Col: <hi>Downs,</hi> to ſpeak with him about it, but he was not there, but about half an hour after the Houſe was ſate, he came in; I removed where he was, and ſate juſt behinde him, and there being a great ſilence in the Houſe, while the Clerk was looking for an Order by Mr. Speakers direction, I ſpake to Col: <hi>Downs</hi> with a very low voyce, thus, Sir, I underſtand you have a charge againſt me, you will do me a favor to give me a copy of it before you report it, that I may be the better enabled to make my defence; he anſwered not a word: whereupon I asked whether he did hear me or no; and withal, ſaid, I do not deſire this as an argument to have you wave it, or that I am careful to anſwer what you ſhall charge me with, but if I know beforehand what you will ſay, I ſhall be the better prepared to ſpeak to it (and for this I have a witneſs that ſate by, Col: <hi>John Bingham</hi> by name) he ſtarted up immediately in a great fit of paſſion, and cryed out, Mr. Speaker, to the Orders of the Houſe; Maſter Speaker, to the Orders of the Houſe; leave being granted him to ſpeak, he ſaid, you were ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but now that your ſecluded Members did you ill offices without door, but I much more fear your Members within door. I do not often trouble you with Speeches, neither would I at this time, but that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:165806:10"/> the Gent. whom it concerns preſt me to give him a Copy of what I am about to ſpeak: I muſt confeſs it lies heavy upon my Spirit, and I can no longer be burthened with it; I acquainted ſome of this Houſe with it ſome days ſince, hoping I ſhould have been called up to make this report, but failing in my expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, and having this opportunity offered me, I ſhall diſcharge my conſcience. About nine or ten days ſince, in the Painted-Chamber, this Gentleman behinde me, Mr. <hi>Fry,</hi> engaged me in a diſcourſe, in which he delivered as his Opinion, and maintained it with Arguments, and quoted Scripture for confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, That Jeſus Chriſt is not God; That Jeſus Chriſt was no more God then he was, but he ſaid, 'tis true, he hath more of God in him then I have, but ſo far as God giveth forth himſelf to me, I am as much God as he is: and this I do poſitively charge him with. To this I immediately anſwered;</p>
            <p>This Gentlemans memory ſerves him well, that he could keep this in his minde nine or ten days without any addition or diminution, but with his favor, Mr. Speaker, his report is very untrue; for firſt, I ſay thus, That I did not believe Jeſus Chriſt to be God, after that maner ſome held him forth; 2. That according to that word Subſiſtence, no more was imported of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt his being in the Godhead, in my judgement, then might be affirmed of me and all other Creatures, according to that in <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 24. <hi>In him we live, &amp; move, and have our being:</hi> And touching the Union of the Saints with Jeſus Chriſt, I ſaid, he was called in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, the Head, and the Saints the Members, now we know that the hand is of the body as well as the head, though the head is more tranſcendently of the body,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:165806:11"/> and it is ſaid, we are made partakers of the Divine Nature; This I ſpake in the Painted-Chamber, by way of Argument, not delivering my Opinion po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively in any thing, and Mr. Speaker, if you can make any thing of this, I muſt ſubmit to you.</p>
            <p>The Houſe fell into ſome debate of it, and it was moved, ſince I was poſitively charged with the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned particulars, though I did as poſitively de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it, yet for the ſatisfaction of the Houſe, I ſhould deliver what my Opinion was in that point, which for reaſons then occurring into my minde, I declined; Thereupon a Vote paſſed I ſhould withdraw; and after I was withdrawn, it was Voted, I ſhould be ſuſpended ſitting in Parliament, till I gave the Houſe ſatisfaction: I took the matter into the moſt ſerious conſideration I could, and ſuppoſing if I did not ſomething according to the pleaſure of the Houſe, it would be ſome blemiſh to my reputation, I drew up my Opinion of the Trinity in the Godhead in a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and delivered it into the hands of a Member of the Houſe, my very good friend, to tender it to the Houſe, which accordingly was done; and after the reading of it, and ſome debate thereupon, I was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored; and for the ſatisfaction of all thoſe to whoſe hands this ſhall come, I have here inſerted it <hi>verbatim.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="opinion">
               <head>The Opinion of <hi>Joh. Fry</hi> of the Trinity of the Godhead, humbly ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to the Honorable Houſe of Commons, to take off, if it may be, all prejudice of Error in that point, that lieth upon him by reaſon of a Charge untruly reported (whether upon miſtake or other ground, I know not) by Col: <hi>John Downs;</hi> Together with his Anſwer to the ſaid Charge.</head>
               <p>BEfore I ſpeak to the aboveſaid particulars, I ſhall take leave to make my apology for not delivering
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:165806:11"/> my opinion at that inſtant, when I was charged, the reaſons that prevailed with me, which occurred then into my memory, were theſe:</p>
               <p>Firſt, I thought my denying the charge was enough to ſatisfie the Houſe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I thought it would much reflect upon me, to be catechized after that maner.</p>
               <p>But conſulting ſince with the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 15. who adviſeth to <hi>be ready to give an account to every man that asketh you a reaſon of the hope that is in you, &amp;c.</hi> I ſhall faithfully deliver my Opinion in the point.</p>
               <p>I do and ever did, ſince I knew any thing of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, really believe, That the Father is God, the Son is God, and the Holy Ghoſt is God, and that theſe three are equally God; That God the Son took our nature, and manifeſted himſelf gloriouſly in it, and in a myſtery, according to the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>And without controverſie, great is the myſtery of godlineſs, which is, God manifeſted in the fleſh, &amp;c.</hi> That the Son remains God for ever, and yet they are not three Gods, but one God.</p>
               <div type="charges_and_answers">
                  <head>My Charge as followeth.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, that I ſhould ſay, I do not believe Jeſus Chriſt to be God.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, that I ſhould ſay, He is no more God then I am: It is true, he hath more of God in him then I have, but ſo far as God giveth forth himſelf to me, I am as much God as he is. Thus far my Charge.</p>
                  <p>To the firſt I anſwer, and this I do as in the preſence of God, That according to the beſt of my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, I did ſay, I did not believe Jeſus Chriſt to be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:165806:12"/> God in that maner that I conceived ſome did hold him forth; for according to my beſt underſtanding of their expreſſions, they make Jeſus Chriſt a diſtinct God from God the Father, and God the Holy Ghoſt, and the like they do of the Father &amp; the Holy Ghoſt, and ſo they hold forth three Gods; and this is not my Opinion alone of them, for I meet with others of the ſame judgement.</p>
                  <p>To the laſt I anſwer, in a word, I deny it totally; for as it was never in my thoughts that Jeſus Chriſt God, is not God, or that I ſhall ever partake of the Eſſence of God, ſo I do abominate the Opinions charged upon me. The end of my paper to the Houſe.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall briefly ſpeak to that groſs and carnal Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of three diſtinct Perſons, or Subſiſtences in the God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>head, and conclude.</p>
                  <p>Perſons or Subſiſtences, are Subſtances, or Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents; as for the word Perſon, I do not underſtand that it can properly be attributed but to man; it is out of doubt with me, that if you ask the moſt part of men what they mean by a Perſon, they wil either tell you 'tis a man, or elſe they are not able to give you any anſwer at all: &amp; for the word Accident, I ſuppoſe none will attribute that to God; for according to my poor skill, that word imports no more but the figure or colour, &amp;c. of a thing, and certainly no man ever ſaw the likeneſs of God, as the Scriptures abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teſtifie; and therefore neither of the words, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or Subſiſtences, can hold forth ſuch a meaning as Accidents in God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his Creed, ſaith, There is one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Father, another of the Son, and another of the Holy Ghoſt; others ſay, That there are three
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:165806:12"/> diſtinct Subſiſtences in God: Well, theſe three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or Subſiſtences, cannot be Accidents, neither do I think it is the meaning of any: Then certainly they muſt be Subſtances; if ſo, then they muſt be created or uncreated, limited or unlimited; if created and limited, then the perſon of the Father is a Creature, the perſon of the Son a Creature, and the perſon of the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> a Creature, which I think none will affirm; if they are not created or limited, then they muſt be uncreated or unlimi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed, for I know no <hi>medium</hi> between created and uncreated, limited and unlimited: If they are uncreated and unlimited, then there are three uncreated and unlimited Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, and ſo conſequently three Gods. For my part, I finde no footing for ſuch expreſſions in Scripture; and I think them fit onely to keep igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant people in carnal and groſs thoughts of God, and therefore I do explode them out of my Creed. I could have come forth in a better dreſs, if I would have made uſe of help, which was offered me; but I rather choſe to be ſeen in a true face, homely garb, and ruſſet coat, then a painted face, borrowed accou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trements, and an hypocritical poſture. A ruſſet coat ſerves the Countreymans turn very well, and ſuits beſt for a man of his profeſsion, and he thinks it comely enough, till he ſtands by a Sattin or Scarlet ſuit, then he ſees what a home ſpun fellow he is; if there be no other benefit of this, but to be a foil to ſet off other mens parts, it will not be altogether uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
